<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Salmonid Ecology Group</title>
 <link href="https://seggothenburg.com//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://seggothenburg.com//"/>
 <updated>2025-04-04T10:28:48+00:00</updated>
 <id>https://seggothenburg.com</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Brook Trout; A Management Conundrum in Swedish Streams</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/brook-trout-a-management-conundrum"/>
   <updated>2025-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/brook-trout-a-management-conundrum</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With their bright red markings with blue borders the brook trout (&lt;em&gt;Salvelinus fontinalis&lt;/em&gt;) is a charismatic fish popular with Swedish anglers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brook trout are also often a species of interest with SEG and for good reason. Brook trout inhabit a variety of habitats from small streams and ponds to larger rivers and lakes favouring the colder waters of eastern North America. The wide habitat preference and diverse life cycles have arisen from several distinct genetic lineages of the species including some anadromous populations colloquially called “salters” in the eastern United States. Most populations will remain in freshwater systems; however, growth and development can vary greatly with habitat size and water temperature. Brook trout inhabiting warmer smaller streams are smaller (maxing out at 300mm) and typically mature in 2 years but as little as 1 year with an average life span of 5-7 years. Larger colder lakes and rivers have been found supporting larger brook trout (4-4.5 kg and up to 9-10 years). Spawning occurs in gravel beds of streams with ground water percolation or spring fed areas of lakes. After emerging in earl spring (February to April) young brook trout will progress from feeding on plankton to insects and just about anything smaller that drifts by them. Their diet is wide due to drift feeding and contains a significant terrestrial component from insects falling into streams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/mitch1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brook trout&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Invasive brook trout caught for behavioral studies at Gothenburg University.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brook trout in their native range represent a conservation concern with human modifications to habitats, unregulated harvest in the late 1800’s, dams preventing instream migration, siltation of gravel beds and warming water temperatures has resulted in widespread decline in brook trout populations. Conservation of native populations is fraught with competition with invasive species, further fragmentation of populations and habitat, range contraction through climate change and difficulties with brook trout historical range covering multijurisdictional boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the decline in their native range, the North American native is a relative newcomer being introduced to Swedish and European water ways. Introduced in the late 1800’s, they have proliferated to the point of being considered one of Europe’s top invasive aquatic species (Savini et al. 2010). Of special concern is the effect on native brown trout having replaced brown trout in several boreal lakes of northern Sweden and reducing brown trout populations in many southern streams and lakes. This competition with brown trout impacts not only brown trout and their structural role in fresh and saltwater systems, but also the endangered freshwater pearl mussel (Margaritifera margaritifera). Freshwater pearl mussels in Swedish water ways require brown trout hosts for glochidia to parasitize for development and dispersal. Freshwater pearl mussel glochidia are not able to effectively parasitize the new (in evolutionary terms) brook trout and studies have found that encystment on brook trout gills often fails or results in smaller less viable juvenile mussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/mitch2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Life cycle&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Simplified life cycle of freshwater pearl mussel in Swedish waterways.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success of brook trout in Swedish water ways is attributed to numerous factors such as early maturation, larger size at hatching and behavioral changes such as increased aggression and piscivory in nonnative systems. Further complications come from a ‘habitat disturbance paradox’, niche convergence resulting in more direct &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/invasive-species-interactions-diet-and-personality&quot;&gt;competition with brown trout&lt;/a&gt; and evolutionary mechanisms such as the enemy release hypothesis. The habitat disturbance paradox seen with brook trout is nonnative populations exhibiting increased tolerances to temperature changes and habitat disturbance that have resulted in extirpation in their native range. Enemy release hypothesis is the idea that invasive species are less impacted by enemies than native species; the parasitism of brown trout by freshwater pearl mussel but not brook trout frees brook trout from the fitness cost of co-existing with the mussel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way that brook trout management represents two very different aspects of conservation biology shows the many dilemmas biologists and stakeholders face. Outside of their native range brook trout represent an invader; highly resilient to removal and impacting multiple species and many stakeholder interests. Inside their historical range they are a species pushed to extirpation across vast areas due to a plethora of invasive species, human modification to habitat, and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Mitch Olson, Master’s student with SEG&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mitch is a Canadian biologist who has previously worked across western Canada for 4 years as an environmental consultant before attending the University of Gothenburg to further his education. He is currently a second-year maters student in conservation biology in the Department of Biology and Environmental Sciences at the University of Gothenburg. He is currently completing a masters thesis under the supervision of Johan Höjesjö. His thesis is attempting to correlate brook trout removal method with behavioral and phenotypic characteristics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How do Boat Induced Waves Affect Göta älv and the Atlantic Sturgeon?</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/how-do-boat-induced-waves-affect-atlantic-sturgeon"/>
   <updated>2025-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/how-do-boat-induced-waves-affect-atlantic-sturgeon</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Several vessels navigate the Göta River daily, and the wake waves from larger ships can damage, impact, or displace the benthic fauna and fish eggs in the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, in turn, reduces their survival chances, as well as those of fish species such as the newly introduced Atlantic sturgeon (&lt;em&gt;Acipenser oxyrinchus&lt;/em&gt;), which feeds on benthic invertebrates during its juvenile stage (Näslund et al., n.d.). Additionally, the waves from ships erode shallow shoreline habitats, altering fish habitats and affecting species with specific requirements for spawning and nursery areas. Lithophilic fish species are particularly sensitive to high-frequency wake waves (Zajicek &amp;amp; Wolter, 2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/erik1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Vessel in Göta River&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; A photo of the ship TUNA in Göta älv which has a length of 89 meters and a width of 13.35 meters. The vessel causes a lot of waves on certain locations in the river, esepcially closer to Lilla edet. Photo: Erik Fransson&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boat-induced wake waves also increase the detachment of benthic invertebrates from substrates, particularly in simpler habitats with low structural complexity. Studies have also shown that the long-term effects of boat traffic waves lead to reduced biodiversity and changes in the food web (Gabel, 2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/public/images/erik2.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Atlantic sturgeon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; How will boat waves affect the newly released Atlantic sturgeon in Göta älv? Photo: https://storensaterkomst.se/&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer of 2024, 95 individuals of Atlantic sturgeon were released into the Göta River as part of the Sportfiskarna project &lt;a href=&quot;https://storensaterkomst.se/&quot;&gt;Störens återkomst&lt;/a&gt;. This species had been extinct in the river for over 100 years due to overfishing, but with the approval of the County Administrative Board, juvenile individuals from the Leibniz Institute of Freshwater Ecology and Inland Fisheries (IGB) in Berlin were reintroduced into the river (Sportfiskarna, 2023).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Atlantic sturgeon now faces additional challenges, such as limited food availability in the river, which may be influenced by the impact of ship wakes. Surveys have also noted very low populations of pike eggs in the Göta and Nordre Rivers. Only three pike eggs were found in the Göta River and 12 in the Nordre River during the 2021 survey (Sportfiskarna, 2021). This may be due to the wake waves from pilot boats destroying their spawning areas (Sportfiskarna, 2021).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This master thesis has just started and aims to carefully map and analyze the river area from Jordfallsbron to Lilla Edet. The goal is to identify locations where waves have the greatest negative impact on organisms or where the physical force of the waves is strongest. This will provide a better opportunity to protect the Atlantic sturgeon, benthic fauna, and fish eggs more sustainably, for example, through speed restrictions or wake protection measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Erik Fransson, Master’s student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Erik is currently a second-year master’s student in marine biology at the Department of marine science at the University of Gothenburg. Currently, under the supervision of Johan Höjesjö and Linnéa Jägrud in the cooperation of Sportfiskarna, he is undertaking his master’s thesis, which focuses on the effects and mapping of ship-induced waves on benthic fauna and fish eggs in göta älv with a focus on the Atlantic sturgeon. The purpose of this study is to investigate the effects of ship-induced waves from larger vessels in the Göta River and how they impact the benthic fauna (primarily invertebrates), fish eggs (primarily pike eggs), and how this in turn affects fish in the Göta River, with a focus on the Atlantic sturgeon. The aim is also to identify which areas in the channel need speed restrictions or other forms of protection (for example, longitudinal barriers or other types of wave protection).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Invasive species interactions, diet and personality</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/invasive-species-interactions-diet-and-personality"/>
   <updated>2025-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/invasive-species-interactions-diet-and-personality</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How does it all fit together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I our recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ece3.70995?af=R&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; we’ve been investigating how invasion of brook trout, &lt;em&gt;Salvelinus fontinalis&lt;/em&gt;, affects the behavior and diet of native brown trout, &lt;em&gt;Salmo trutta&lt;/em&gt;, in Swedish streams. When brook and brown trout live side by side in the stream we have made some interesting observations. We found that the native brown trout adjust their feeding habits — often leading to a convergence in diet between the two species! However this effect appears to be dependent on what the ratio of brook to brown is, because the convergence was not present in the stream where the brook trout outnumbered the brown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our work, we’ve also discovered a fascinating link between personality traits and dietary choices: bolder brown trout tend to hold a higher trophic position. This suggests that their willingness to take risks might allow them access to different or more abundant food resources compared to less bold individuals. These results indicate that behavioral variation within a species can significantly influence how individuals adapt when new competition is introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS. How did we know which fish were bold? Read about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/boldness-in-trout&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Benedikte Austad, PhD student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How do we measure behaviour?</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/boldness-in-trout"/>
   <updated>2025-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/boldness-in-trout</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why do fish behave the way they do, and…
&lt;!--more--&gt;
how do we measure behaviour?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying behaviour in animals is challenging, we can’t simply ask a bird or a fish why they are acting in a certain way, so, we must come up with other methods to interpret behaviour. In SEG we have a wide range of projects focusing on salmonid behaviour and are always working to refine our methods. One aspect of behaviour we are particularly interested in is boldness. Boldness, sometimes referred to as ‘the propensity to engage in risky behaviour’, is a trait that varies widely between individuals and ecological contexts. Measuring boldness boils down to introducing an individual to something new and seeing how they react. In fish we largely see two strategies: freezing or interacting/moving. We can then use these responses to determine how shy or bold an individual is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our boldness test we record fish as they encounter a novel environment, initially keeping the fish in total darkness and then exposing them to daylight. Salmonids are sensitive to changes in light and we use this sudden change to elicit a startle response. During a 5-minute period fish that move around the enclosure are categorised as bold and those that freeze are categorised as shy. So far, using this method we have been able to demonstrate differences in boldness across two contexts. 1) Smaller trout are bolder than larger trout and 2) Early migrating trout are bolder than late migrating trout. Determining how, and why, behaviours differ between individuals is key to helping us understand wider concepts such as niche expansion, dispersal and patterns relating to life history traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more check out our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0376635725000245?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;new paper&lt;/a&gt; in Behavioural Processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Madeleine Berry, PhD student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Eelgrass and sea trout project 2024 field season</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/eelgrass-project-first-post"/>
   <updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/eelgrass-project-first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the field season of 2024 we PIT-tagged migrating smolts in four streams along the Swedish west coast and followed up by conducting a beach seine net survey in the coastal area adjacent to the streams. &lt;!--more--&gt;  The survey provided information about prey choice of sea trout and species community in each area. Additionally, we collected epifaunal samples in each coastal area to estimate prey abundance and benthic community composition in eelgrass meadows and unvegetated sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the autumn, we visited cormorant colonies around our sites to investigate potential cormorant predation of our PIT-tagged sea trout. By using portable antennas, we scanned for PIT-tags around the colonies used by the cormorant during the spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/eab8dbe9-1af2-4072-9057-3fc0a0f17d39&quot; alt=&quot;Field work&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Field work during 2024. Photos: Magnus Lovén Wallerius and Karl Karlsson&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/6771011f-4006-4fcb-a047-4567f2063d11&quot; alt=&quot;Various prey&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Various prey found in sea trout stomachs. Photo: Karl Karlsson&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/7fe71b4f-1cf9-4f12-afc2-4c1c4ec4da40&quot; alt=&quot;Various prey&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Scanning of cormorant colonies. Photo: Magnus Lovén Wallerius&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2025, we are planning to conduct an acoustic telemetry study to assess habitat use of sea trout smolt in an area with both eelgrass meadows and unvegetated sites. This study will increase the knowledge of how these habitats influence residence time and diel activity patterns of sea trout in coastal areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also conduct a mark-recapture study, using passive fyke nets, in an area that contains both eelgrass meadows and unvegetated sites. Not only will we potentially recapture tagged sea trout and measure growth at sea, but also collect stomach content data of untagged sea trout to quantify prey choice in different habitats. In collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.8fjordar.se/&quot;&gt;8-fjordar&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slu.se/&quot;&gt;SLU&lt;/a&gt; we will also PIT-tag and measure other fish species to quantify the fish community and different tropic levels that would impact the trophic chain in the eelgrass meadows. By targeting and tagging more fish species in this area, we could also get a better understanding of how cormorant predation could limit the recovery of important fish species and their impact on eelgrass meadows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Scales of Stress</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/scales-of-stress"/>
   <updated>2024-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/scales-of-stress</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How Fish Populations Handle Stress Differently&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stress is a ubiquitous part of life and one we are all familiar with. As humans we can easily recognise the signs of stress and are aware of the wide range of long-term effects stress can have. We develop various coping mechanisms or tools to help us deal with everyday stressors, but everyone experiences and deals with stress in their own way. For some people giving a presentation at work may elicit a high level of stress, for others they may experience little to no stress but are instead highly stressed by moving house. People experience the same stressor in different ways and to different levels. Well, it turns out the same is true of fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our recently published &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/ece3.11526&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt;, we explore how where a fish is born influences how it copes with stress. Like us, fish also experience a wide range of stressors in their daily lives, from encountering a predator to changes in the water around them. When a fish encounters a stressor, the brain perceives it and sends an array of signals through the body. These signals are communicated through hormones such as cortisol and adrenaline. As different parts of the body receive changes in hormone levels a variety of physiological and behavioural changes take place. Heart rate increases, the spleen contracts to increase circulating red blood cells, they may flee to escape the stressor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within one stream individuals of the same species occupy different sections. In the case of juvenile brown trout, &lt;em&gt;Salmo trutta&lt;/em&gt;, where an individual is found is related to several factors including where their parents chose to spawn, habitat quality and the number of other individuals in the area. All these factors can contribute to the type of individual produced. In our study we focused on how response to a stressor, in this case being chased, differed between fish produced in the furthest upstream section of a stream and a downstream section close to the river mouth. We found that fish from downstream had a stronger response to stress, indicated by parameters such as higher levels of cortisol and higher levels of circulating red blood cells, compared to fish upstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why is it important to understand how individuals differ in different stream sections? Freshwater systems are increasingly under human-induced pressures that are shaping the environment these fish find themselves in. Habitat fragmentation, for example through restructuring of streams or construction of barriers, cuts off individuals from previously accessible areas. If fish from these different sections differ this could have knock on effects for the types of traits we find in a stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have established there is local variation in stress response within a stream we are keen to see what other differences there may be between individuals in different streams sections. We have ongoing work based on this and are hoping to uncover differences in behaviours like aggression and boldness as well as morphological characteristics such as fin size and body shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Madeleine Berry, PhD student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Catch up with SEG</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/catch-up-with-seg"/>
   <updated>2023-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/catch-up-with-seg</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Autumn 2023 has seen another busy season for the members of SEG, let’s see what everyone’s been up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johan and Madeleine spent the last week in the beautiful city of Evora, Portugal where WGTRUTTA members gathered for their biannual meeting. The group had the opportunity to reflect on all that was achieved during the last three years of WGTRUTTA2 and make plans for WGTRUTTA3. They were also lucky enough to get a chance to visit Campelo Aquaculture facility, where fascinating research is being conducted on wild-reared trout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/c5ce59e5-7e2e-484d-a427-47d751483c27&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in Sweden adult sea trout are returning to our study site in Billdal, ready for the spawning season. We have installed a trap to count and measure all individuals, as well as this a subsample of adults have been PIT tagged and we will track their migration upstream in fine detail. In October we tagged more juveniles ready for the spring migration bringing our total number of tagged individuals in this small system since the MAPS project began up to almost 1000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/8a6f4ff5-1f28-44ed-932b-89472d620ec5&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of other exciting research is going on in the group which now has 6 masters students working on their thesis projects. Ali Khari is investigating pressures on sea trout across their natural range in Europe working closely with Katarina Magnusson from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slu.se//&quot;&gt;SLU&lt;/a&gt;. Another project with a European focus is Shirin Nozad’s who is analysing secondary production in streams from Norway, Sweden, France and Portugal and linking this to juvenile trout. Chandika Nuwansiri is working within the NOBROOK project looking at stable isotope signatures in brown trout after invasive brook trout removal. Mobeen Munir is researching brown trout immune response to freshwater pearl mussel infestation. Evelina Olsen spent the summer in Austria working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wcl.ac.at/en/&quot;&gt;Wassercluster Lunz&lt;/a&gt; to broaden our understanding of brook and brown trout interactions. Aryan Kaura will track adult upstream migration in Haga å, seeing how individuals distribute within the stream. Some interesting results are coming in already so watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, SEG has recruited our youngest member with Benedikte welcoming a baby girl in October! Massive congratulations from the rest of the team!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dam Construction and Removal effect on River Ecosystems and Fish Populations</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/dam-construction-and-removal-effect-on-river-ecosystems-and-fish-populations"/>
   <updated>2023-10-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/dam-construction-and-removal-effect-on-river-ecosystems-and-fish-populations</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dams are structures built across rivers and streams to generate hydroelectric power, provide water for irrigation, control flooding, and provide recreational opportunities. However, dam construction and operation can have significant impacts on river ecosystems and fish populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The construction of dams has various ecological and environmental impacts on river ecosystems and their surrounding habitats. Therefore, it is important to understand the positive and negative impacts of dam construction and removal. Although dams have their benefits, the research indicates direct negative impacts of dams on the biological, chemical, and physical characteristics of rivers and riparian ecosystems, as well as on fish populations. Extinction of fish and aquatic species by preventing migration, destruction of coastal deltas, and disruption of downstream sediment transport essential for habitat maintenance are some of the main impacts of dam construction. Furthermore, dams alter the free-flow upstream ecosystem to a lentic habitat. Changes in temperature and dissolved oxygen levels in the water are some the examples of physical impacts of dams on the river ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important impacts of dam construction on river ecosystems is the alteration of natural flow regimes, which can influence the timing, frequency, and duration of flood events, droughts, and seasonal fluctuations. For example, dams can reduce downstream flows, resulting in less water availability for fish and other aquatic organisms. They can also retain sediment behind the dam, causing erosion downstream and changing the shape and depth of river channels. These changes can negatively affect fish populations by reducing the amount and quality of habitat available for spawning, feeding, and migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/e2516922-4874-4a99-806d-f9bb2b29e0c4&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dam removal is a process to restore and revitalize the river ecosystem. Dam removal rapidly restores connectivity between upstream and downstream and facilitates migration and spawning. Consequently, populations of fish and other aquatic species increase. In addition, dam removal replaces the lentic ecosystem with a lotic ecosystem, which is the river’s natural ecosystem for aquatic communities. Removal of the dam results in erosion and relocation of sediment from the reservoir to the lower river, providing plants and animals with the former underwater level. However, the fate of the washed sediments depends on their characteristics and the rate of dam removal.
Dam removal can have significant impacts on river ecosystems and fish populations. Dam removal can restore natural flow regimes, sediment transport, and channel morphology, which can improve the quantity and quality of fish habitat. For example, the removal of Elwha Dam in Washington State resulted in the restoration of more than 120 kilometers of river habitat and the recovery of several fish species, including salmon and steelhead. Similarly, the removal of Glines Canyon Dam on the Elwha River resulted in the creation of new habitats, such as spawning gravel beds, which increased fish productivity and diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/6a8a3c74-717f-4557-a99b-dd4450a4ddfa&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to improving habitat quality, dam removal can improve fish migration, spawning, and population dynamics. For example, the removal of Edwards Dam on the Kennebec River in Maine, USA, resulted in the recovery of populations of American shad, alewife, and blueback herring that had been cut off from their historic spawning grounds for over 160 years. The effects of dam construction and removal on river ecosystems and fish populations are complex and context-dependent. While dam removal can improve habitat quality and strengthen fish populations by restoring natural flow regimes and removing barriers to migration and spawning, it can also cause short-term disturbance and alter sediment transport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, special attention should be paid to reducing biodiversity loss and other ecological and environmental impacts when planning dam construction and removal.
The long-term impacts of dam construction on ecosystems and biodiversity are rarely considered in planning. It appears that there is a need to change the approach to the evaluation and siting of new dam construction. Alternative methods of energy generation should be given greater consideration and study. There are several sustainable alternatives for power generation that can replace hydroelectric power generated by the dam. For example, solar power, wind power, geothermal power, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balance must be struck between harnessing the hydropower potential and preserving the river ecosystem and fish life cycle. Without the proper planning system, dam construction will only lead to species extinction and ecosystem destruction. Decision-makers should work together to create sustainable and compatible solutions that balance the needs of people and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Ali Khari, Master’s student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Spring and summer in Austria for NOBROOK</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-in-austria"/>
   <updated>2023-10-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/nobrook-in-austria</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This past May until August we finally ran the much anticipated experiments in the artificial stream channels in Lunz Am See, Austria!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early spring until fall of 2023 for the NOBROOK project has been dedicated to the collaborative experiments with previous SEG member and project leader Libor Závorka, who currently works at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wcl.ac.at/index.php/en/&quot;&gt;Wassercluster Lunz&lt;/a&gt;. The facility we used for these experiments is situated with two separate stream channels where water from the nearby lake ran through and we could control parameters such as flow, water level and keep a somewhat constant temperature throughout the hot summer months. We subdivided each of these stream channels into four sections on each side, with buffer zones in between and at the beginning and end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/b5e142b1-aa0c-490e-a75a-74911dfdbc6c&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed for us to have eight different enclosures where we placed different assemblages of either only brown trout or a combination of brown trout and brook trout. Furthermore, brown trout were either wild or hatchery-reared undergone different feeding regimes. All the brook trout we used were wild and caught in local streams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;swiper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/3a0b3f64-86c1-45a3-bb3d-7d0ba83e5cdb&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/495d7992-eaa0-4ebe-a8fb-25f4645bad43&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/9bc8be5f-e238-44cc-a713-063a5a792440&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/71fc4153-f560-4990-87ee-4a867ce7f55c&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-prev&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-next&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-pagination&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the stream sections we created a gradient ranging from a “best” part of the enclosure upstream and the “worst” downstream, with a total of four different shelters. The upstream habitat had coarser substrate and more structures as well as presumably access to more invertebrates for the fish as we would put these in the buffer zones. We used portable antennas to assess which fish was inhabiting the best shelter upstream the most, i.e. holding the best position and most likely being the most dominant/best competitor of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;zoom&quot; onmousemove=&quot;zoom(event)&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/d77f089d-faff-4215-9686-79c3dd4b64a3)&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/d77f089d-faff-4215-9686-79c3dd4b64a3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
  figure.zoom {
    background-position: 50% 50%;
    position: relative;
    width: 500px;
    overflow: hidden;
    cursor: zoom-in;
  }
  figure.zoom img:hover {
    opacity: 0;
  }
  figure.zoom img {
    transition: opacity .5s;
    display: block;
    width: 100%;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  function zoom(e){
    var zoomer = e.currentTarget;
    e.offsetX ? offsetX = e.offsetX : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    e.offsetY ? offsetY = e.offsetY : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    x = offsetX/zoomer.offsetWidth*100
    y = offsetY/zoomer.offsetHeight*100
    zoomer.style.backgroundPosition = x + '% ' + y + '%';
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, each fish underwent several tests of cognition prior to entering the stream channels at a different lab facility where we could carefully monitor their movements and solution to tasks via camera footage. 
When they were done here, tagged and measured they were ready to enter the main experiment; the stream channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/3a15d0a2-f1d6-4c0e-b4a6-318a5fe4cc52&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then allowed for fish to interact freely for ten days under which we filmed them at several occasions during the morning, day, evening and night, as well as tracked them with both stationary and portable antennas. The behavioural interactions will be assessed from the video data, the antenna data has already given us valuable data on the dominance status and the social organization of the fish within the enclosures under both high and low water conditions (this was changed during the ten day run).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the final day all the brown trout were sampled. They were weighed, measured, their stomach content collected, muscle samples for isotope analysis were taken as well as brain samples for fatty acid analysis. Additionally, we took their otoliths in order to examine the occurrence of vaterite (abnormal calcite polymorph, see picture below where most of the otolith consists of this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/48313707-84ab-4ec9-a922-22c1f7aa0730&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this data will result in a lot of new insights into the interactions between brook trout and brown trout in terms of aggression and territoriality, as well as how different diets and hatchery conditions affect brown trout’s ability to compete and interact with others in a semi-wild environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, a lot of interesting findings will come of this, but for now the massive amounts of data are being processed so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sea Trout, Essential Facts, and Significance!</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/sea-trout-essential-facts-and-significance"/>
   <updated>2023-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/sea-trout-essential-facts-and-significance</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sea Trout, Essential Facts, and Significance!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brown trout, &lt;em&gt;Salmo trutta&lt;/em&gt;, is a prominent salmonid species with a wide distribution across Northern and Western Europe, spanning from the White Sea to the Mediterranean and encompassing the entire Baltic Sea region. The anadromous form of brown trout, known as the sea trout, has a latitude from northern Scandinavia to northern Africa. Sea trout migrates from its native river or streams to the sea, where it forages until reaching sexual maturity, and then returns to its home river for spawning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/d95059f9-40e9-4dc9-affc-c36484d929fd&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea trout differ from their close relatives, the salmon, in that sea trout are found in smaller streams and tributaries to larger rivers along the entire coast, and exhibit a more complex life history. It does not migrate as much as salmon and spends most of its life cycle in the sea and coastal waters. However, it’s worth noting that certain populations of sea trout, especially those in the southern Baltic, undertake longer migrations to reach open waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The migration patterns of sea trout populations exhibit diversity. Some adult fish remain within their river environment throughout their life cycle, while adults in other populations make feeding migrations to coastal sea areas, where they feed on invertebrates and small fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea trout, as predatory fish, play a structural role in ecosystem dynamics, particularly through top-down control at the lower trophic levels. They hold significant ecological, social, and economic importance for local communities across Northern Europe. Sea trout support important fisheries and encourage river conservation efforts. Sea trout play an important role in maintaining equilibrium within riverine food webs. They achieve this by both harvesting invertebrate populations and serving as a crucial food source for other predatory species. Additionally, sea trout contribute to both aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems by facilitating the transport of nutrients and energy from the sea to the lotic ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the life cycle of sea trout, individuals live as parr in streams for the initial 1 to 5 years of their lives. Following this period, parr undergoes smoltification, adopting a silver appearance and acquiring the physiological adaptations required for marine life. Subsequently, they embark on migrations to the sea, where they spend up to 5 years feeding, primarily on forage fish, before returning to their native streams for spawning. They exhibit a preference for smaller rivers and streams with swift currents, often selecting upper reaches and tributaries that provide suitable nursery areas. Spawning occurs during the autumn and winter months, with each female typically laying around 10,000 eggs in well-suited gravel beds. These eggs hatch in the spring, contingent on suitable water temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/d7c98359-ed20-4177-9b81-c0054bff146e&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea trout is one of the two most important salmonids in the Baltic Sea. Despite the historical significance of sea trout in this region, it faces challenges. Currently classified as vulnerable in the Baltic Sea, there are only 500 remaining natural populations. Urgent measures are required to restore sea trout stocks and river conditions, given the impact of past management practices. To achieve this, it is crucial to gather data on river status and sea trout population. This information aids in comprehending the present state, understanding past trends, and formulating plans for future actions.
Sea trout have historically ranked second only to Atlantic salmon in national fisheries assessment programs and management priorities. As sea trout and other dispersed fish species fall under EU policy areas, such as the Common Fisheries Policy (CFP) and the Marine Strategy Framework Directive (MSFD), it becomes imperative to enhance methods for assessing and monitoring stock status. This holistic approach ensures the conservation and sustainable management of this valuable species in the Baltic Sea and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Ali Khari, Master’s student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ali is currently a second-year master’s student in biology at the Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences at the University of Gothenburg. Currently, under the supervision of Johan Höjesjö and in the cooperation of ICES WGTRUTTA, he is undertaking his master’s thesis, which focuses on exploring the impact of various human factors on sea trout populations in different European countries. His aim in this thesis is to assess the impact of various anthropogenic pressures such as Fisheries, Habitat Degradation, Barriers, Climate Change, etc. on the Sea Trout recruitment index in different regions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Salmon or trout?</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/blog/salmon-or-trout"/>
   <updated>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//blog/salmon-or-trout</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ever wondered…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salmon or trout?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atlantic salmon, &lt;em&gt;Salmo salar&lt;/em&gt; and brown trout, &lt;em&gt;Salmo trutta&lt;/em&gt; are two closely related salmonid species that are often mistaken for one another. At the juvenile stage they can be tricky to tell apart, especially given that the classic trout/salmon ‘markers’ may not always be clear or present in every individual. For example, one frequently used marker is red colouration in the adipose fin which identifies an individual as trout and no red as salmon, however occasionally some trout lack this colouration as well and the frequency of which this occurs varies locally. Therefore, it is recommended to use several indicators.
Here we can see some of the commonly used indicators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;zoom&quot; onmousemove=&quot;zoom(event)&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/21cae585-9cc8-43e6-b60d-610de146736e)&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/21cae585-9cc8-43e6-b60d-610de146736e&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
  figure.zoom {
    background-position: 50% 50%;
    position: relative;
    width: 500px;
    overflow: hidden;
    cursor: zoom-in;
  }
  figure.zoom img:hover {
    opacity: 0;
  }
  figure.zoom img {
    transition: opacity .5s;
    display: block;
    width: 100%;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  function zoom(e){
    var zoomer = e.currentTarget;
    e.offsetX ? offsetX = e.offsetX : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    e.offsetY ? offsetY = e.offsetY : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    x = offsetX/zoomer.offsetWidth*100
    y = offsetY/zoomer.offsetHeight*100
    zoomer.style.backgroundPosition = x + '% ' + y + '%';
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;zoom&quot; onmousemove=&quot;zoom(event)&quot; style=&quot;background-image: url(https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/e374c214-35f2-4632-bacf-09ccc1effd96)&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/e374c214-35f2-4632-bacf-09ccc1effd96&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
  figure.zoom {
    background-position: 50% 50%;
    position: relative;
    width: 500px;
    overflow: hidden;
    cursor: zoom-in;
  }
  figure.zoom img:hover {
    opacity: 0;
  }
  figure.zoom img {
    transition: opacity .5s;
    display: block;
    width: 100%;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  function zoom(e){
    var zoomer = e.currentTarget;
    e.offsetX ? offsetX = e.offsetX : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    e.offsetY ? offsetY = e.offsetY : offsetX = e.touches[0].pageX
    x = offsetX/zoomer.offsetWidth*100
    y = offsetY/zoomer.offsetHeight*100
    zoomer.style.backgroundPosition = x + '% ' + y + '%';
  }
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by Madeleine Berry, PhD student with the SEG.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS in Portugal</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-portugal"/>
   <updated>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-portugal</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;MAPS heads south!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September the MAPS project headed to Portugal to join the team from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mare-centre.pt/en&quot;&gt;MARE&lt;/a&gt; for their annual salmonid sampling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrofishing surveys were carried out in over 20 sites in the Minho and Lima river basins. These regions are particularly interesting for salmonid migration research as they are the southern limit for anadromous salmonids. During the fieldwork all trout, salmon and sea lamprey were caught and measured and salmonids &amp;gt;10cm were PIT tagged. Next spring a smolt trap will be installed in Minho and we can see if any of the tagged individuals migrate out to sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At two sites additional behavioural study was carried out. Juvenile trout were scored for boldness and the hope is to see how boldness links to the decision to migrate. This work will go into a larger European effort investigating migration patterns across a latitudinal gradient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to Sara, Carlos, André and Esmeralda for all their help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;swiper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/8ede9c59-529f-4a71-9314-a027bdf9f7b9&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/b5ca6697-3375-4a6f-92fe-713e47124854&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/2a56d69e-4387-47aa-a1de-fa3ec57d56c1&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/ee5d46f9-4271-43e6-8ae5-cfba1e86a569&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/7e7334c4-82a3-419c-b693-5846aa8f3608&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/9243e5f9-a966-4d08-93e8-e12dcbbce68b&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/benediau/seg-gbg/assets/96004332/acb1f4ce-2847-483f-b399-7eee7245bdc9&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-prev&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-next&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-pagination&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Autumn and winter for the NOBROOK project</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-fall-and-winter"/>
   <updated>2023-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/nobrook-fall-and-winter</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Progress is being made for the NOBROOK project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this fall we have removed brook trout from one of our study streams in Borås. This process involved fishing the whole stream twice using electro fishing with the help of our collaborators at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportfiskarna.se/&quot;&gt; Sportfiskarna&lt;/a&gt;. We did this before spawning time to reduce the reproductive success for the brook trout and ensure that we could remove the vast majority of brook trout in the stream. While fishing we also found evidence that spawning between brook trout and brown trout has been ocurring, because we fished several tiger trout. See the video at the bottom to get a close up look at this interesting hybrid!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/218515409-ff732a89-6c84-4230-a3d2-b721f34ba336.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward the plan is to examine the effects this removal has had on brown trout in terms of behavior and ecological niche. Several of the brook trout we removed have contributed in different ways back in the warmth of the lab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have artificially infested both brook trout and brown trout with larvae of the freshwater pearl mussel in the lab at zoologen. Our master’s student, Isac (as seen in the picture above to the right), has used these fish for experiments testing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;i)	Whether brook trout may serve as suitable hosts for the glochidia larvae, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ii)	How infestation of the brown trout affects their dominance in one-on-one competition situations with both brook trout and conspecifics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His thesis will be finished soon and will contribute to WP4 of the NOBROOK project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When keeping the brook trout in the aquariums at zoologen we also wanted to test the potential for social traps as an effective catch method. This experiment is still going on, and should there be clear indications that baiting a trap with another brook trout is effective we will consider expanding this to the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until next time, please enjoy this video!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6DdiA0EUTno&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New year for MAPS</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/new-year-for-maps"/>
   <updated>2023-02-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/new-year-for-maps</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new year for MAPS with lots of exciting work in the pipeline! Plans for a habitat mapping workshop, setting up new stationary antennas and fieldwork in sunny Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first let’s check in with what we got up to in 2022:
A large part of the work conducted in Sweden involved running traps for both downstream migrating juveniles in the spring and upstream migrating adults in the fall. Now we have a comprehensive view of the sea trout population in our study stream and smolt productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a big PIT tagging effort from the team in three countries. With help from collaborators in the ICES working group WGTRUTTA we now have hundreds of juveniles in Sweden, Norway and France tagged ready to follow their journey to sea come spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/216825321-d6ff575e-b51f-4569-b1ba-2dedbe9533c8.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample analysis is under way on two fronts. Tissue collected from individuals coming through the trap is being analysed to determine sex. This will give us a picture of what the sex ratio of outward migrating smolts is like in our study stream. As well as this, ventricles are being processed to investigate how heart structure differs between offspring with differing parental migration strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/216825379-27e58f81-f8e6-4315-97fb-2401a5e5cc7d.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s hope for another successful year in 2023!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS in Norway</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-norway"/>
   <updated>2022-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-norway</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;SEG heads North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team headed back to Northern Norway in September to begin sampling juvenile sea trout. Nestled in the mountains of Kjerringøy is a highly productive lake system called Fjærvatn where we have established 3 sites. Each site was habitat mapped and sampled for benthic invertebrates, this data will be used with other sites across Europe to develop tools to predict smolt productivity.
With help from Lars Rønning from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntnu.no/&quot;&gt;NTNU&lt;/a&gt; we caught and PIT tagged 155 young trout across the 3 sites. In the spring (after the ice thaws) we will put up 3 stationary antenna and track their movement out to sea. Until then we have plenty of morphometric and behavioural data to analyse, looking for differences between populations of varying distance to sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;swiper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191457780-e98aa577-68f2-4b75-9d37-87e8344eb6d0.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191457944-00d4b7b5-290d-48bb-b06b-1bf2c701394f.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191458052-55a20b40-c30d-40ac-bd6d-6a750f058fd4.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191458136-1abe4f5f-45ef-4a74-a052-b2a243f61d01.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191458225-d6fa3177-7e6b-43d1-a9c0-fd186a871b29.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/191458444-163e6446-0be0-4792-b1de-c906882187e9.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-prev&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-next&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-pagination&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS Summer 2022</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-summer-2022"/>
   <updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-summer-2022</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of May Johan and Madeleine set off to France for a few days to check out a potential stream site for the MAPS project. &lt;!--more--&gt; They headed to a small brook section of the river Oir in the countryside of Rennes and had the chance to join the team at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inrae.fr/en&quot;&gt; INRAE&lt;/a&gt; during one of their annual monitoring studies. The narrow brook is a very productive spawning area for both brown trout and Atlantic salmon and is regularly surveyed three times a year. SEG return in the autumn to work with them again sampling and PIT tagging some of the juvenile trout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/182793047-ac4a2dc0-2907-4838-9da7-727aeda0bee8.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June it was time to head over to Northwest Norway for habitat mapping and invertebrate sampling in the system at Beiarn, this data will used in the predictive modelling work for the MAPS project. We also took the chance to visit the lake system at Kjerringöy where we plan to sample and tag fish in September for the work on migratory patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/182793468-b055c068-e048-489c-b945-0dce24014288.JPG&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Madeleine is presenting her project plan and preliminary findings with a poster at the International Society of Behavioural Ecology Conference 2022 in Stockholm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/182793821-5036e21f-9abb-47a0-bd84-373bd527d38f.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NOBROOK Spring 2022</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-second-post"/>
   <updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/nobrook-second-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The spring has been a busy time for the NOBROOK project! &lt;!--more--&gt; Each of the experimental stream sections have been habitat mapped this spring and each stretch has been given a score of the quality of trout habitat (THS). This data will allow us to determine the quality of habitat being utilized when we combine this with the telemetry data we have collected through the fall of last year, late winter and early spring of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/181914961-a5a4cde4-16c1-4e8a-a088-470ee91a1acb.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in June each stretched was electro fished and more fish of both species were tagged and boldness score, the fish that we managed to recapture from last fall’s tagging were also scored this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the field work that’s been done in Borås, we also had the chance to visit our collaborator and friend Libor in Lunz, Austria. The plan moving forward is hopefully to work together on some experiments there next summer. In order to get a more detailed perspective of the effects of remvoing brook trout with different behavioural triats we will be conducting these experiments in artificial stream channels located in Lunz. This will be conducted as a supplement to the field based approach taking place in Borås.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/181915174-27ceffd2-6563-4779-8df0-40a12146db9c.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan for the time being is to examine the behavioral phenotypes of the fish (brown and brook trout that will be caught in Austria), and we will design the
enclosures so as to create different subhabitats of different qualities. This will allow us to
determine which fish is the most dominant one as the most dominant fish will inhabit the best
habitat (i.e. the most stable water flow and best food supply), and we will subsequently remove
this fish and observing the response of the remaining population. The enclosures will emulate
both sympatric sections with both species, as well as allopatric sections with only brown trout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SEG April Newsletter</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/SEG-april"/>
   <updated>2022-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/SEG-april</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fieldwork season has begun!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team has been enjoying the sunshine while collecting data for both the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/nobrook/&quot;&gt;NOBROOK&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/maps/&quot;&gt;MAPS&lt;/a&gt; projects this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In NOBROOK the 8 streams in Borås are starting to be habitat mapped to develop a trout habitat score for each one. Tracking of the tagged fish is complete for now so once we have the rest of the habitat data Kim and Christian will be able to see how the fish are utilizing the habitat at each site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/166258872-d8fb2167-aceb-474c-8c35-377bd092e5f4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In MAPS the focus has been on the smolt trap in Haga å, Billdal. The trap went up early April and already several hundred smolts have been through, including some of the fish we tagged last Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/166257535-6d91cb47-c6f5-4214-a98a-2eef6fa9a3db.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each fish has been measured and assessed for smoltification status. Our bachelor’s student Emelie will be analyzing what kind of relationship there is between discharge/temperature and peaks in migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/166257717-2728508f-86a0-415e-8f26-eb75c636d112.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Zoologen Magnus and Christian have been hard at work preparing for an exciting eel project investigating fish ladders and glass eels. Everything is ready to go and the experiment begins now, we look forward to seeing what the eels do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More newsletters to come about SEG activities, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SEG March Newsletter</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/SEG-march"/>
   <updated>2022-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/SEG-march</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The SEG is getting ready for spring! 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off a massive congratulations to Dr. Niklas Wengström on completing his PhD! It was great to hear the culmination of his many years of hard work and dedication in his thesis &lt;em&gt;“Parasite host interaction between the freshwater pearl mussel (Margaritifera margaritifera) and brown trout (Salmo trutta), the impact from glochidia larvae on the host”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Niklas’ defence SEG held a workshop where several members of SEG got to both present their research and hear about the research of the visiting academics that made up Niklas’ committee. There was a diverse range of topics and it was fantastic to mingle and share ideas in person again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/159933727-f81bee65-b81a-4baa-9258-220c105b32d8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of effort preparing samples Benedikte has sent fin clips and invertebrates from the stream sites in Borås to the lab for isotope analysis. We look forward to getting the results in a few weeks. In the meantime more tracking has been done for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/nobrook/&quot;&gt;NOBROOK&lt;/a&gt; project by Kim and Christian and planning for the upcoming field season is underway which will include further mapping and examinig of the stream habitats and tagging of fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/159935051-1a71fa12-ef85-4ce2-8419-bc7354ac6dee.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/159939617-5c2c0de6-7e2b-4a50-a1a8-76bd70df2dc0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/maps/&quot;&gt;MAPS&lt;/a&gt; project the focus has been on getting the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/maps/2022/03/21/maps-antennas/&quot;&gt;stationary antenna system&lt;/a&gt; and smolt trap up and running before the juvenile sea trout start migrating in early April. There are now 3 functioning antenna in the stream and it is hoped another one will be built in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The location of the smolt trap has been decided and construction has begun with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;http://miljoteknikivast.se/&quot;&gt;Miljöteknik i Väst&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/159935342-06b3be1e-0177-4ecd-8e4c-f6cf0e1510f7.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/159935476-b2f69862-9c79-4c94-bcac-89e98f403398.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More newsletters to come about SEG activities, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Stationary antennas for MAPS</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-antennas"/>
   <updated>2022-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-antennas</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The antennas are working!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of trial and error the stationary PIT antenna system is up and running at the lower site in Haga å, Billdal. We faced several challenges getting the antenna in place at this site, from electrical interference in the tunnel to logs in the stream tearing them down during bad weather. But now, &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt;, there are functioning antenna where we need them to see the juveniles migrate to sea. Just in time too as the tagged juveniles will start to migrate in the next couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built two antennas so we can determine which direction the fish are swimming in and be sure when they have migrated. The main objective is to see whether there is variation in migratory patterns between populations born very far upstream and those born closer to the river mouth. Things to look out for will be date of migration, time of migration, do they move in groups, what is the temperature in the stream when they migrate and do more bold individuals migrate faster?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they enter estuary the fish will likely stay in the local coastal area, here they will have access to nutrient rich food that will aid their growth. In a few years they will return to the stream system to spawn, by which time they will have grown much larger than their resident counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ilicZ4UyKJg&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SEG February Newsletter</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/SEG-february"/>
   <updated>2022-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/SEG-february</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The SEG is hard at work! 
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week Niklas nailed his thesis titled &lt;em&gt;“Parasite host interaction between the freshwater  pearl mussel (Margaritifera margaritifera) and brown trout (Salmo trutta), the impact from glochidia larvae on the host”&lt;/em&gt; at Zoologen. His &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gu.se/evenemang/niklas-wengstrom-parasite-host-interaction-between-the-freshwater-pearl-mussel-margaritifera-margaritifera-and-brown-trout-salmo-trutta-the-impact&quot;&gt;defense&lt;/a&gt; will take place on the 11th of March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155166595-4cce6d3e-222d-48db-b173-3bd1f68e0595.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155166689-0057b648-e77f-405b-8ed5-2a853897f6df.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting bachelor and master projects are underway. Pernilla is working hard on identifying the insects caught at the study sites connected to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/nobrook/&quot;&gt;NOBROOK&lt;/a&gt; project, data which she will use as the basis for her thesis about the effects on the benthic invertebrate composition as a result of the brook and brown trout interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155167686-de762c7a-52c9-434e-a26a-af635dde4ec8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155167855-96bc7169-601d-42d5-b643-87294be94297.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matilda is busy with data analysis and report writing for her thesis work on juvenile sea trout investigating behavioral differences between offspring of long and short distance migrants. Sebastian is gearing up to start his field work soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEG members and up-and-coming bachelor and master students have been back at the study sites checking the winter conditions of the NOBROOK streams as well, and provided the weather and water levels allow for it; the fish will be tracked with portable antennas during the coming weeks and will provide valuable data for the NOBROOK project, as well as interesting thesis material about the winter locations of the brook and brown trout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155168935-5bd69ce9-1a68-4051-929b-bf2578b05c3f.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155169071-8189acf9-d855-463d-bf3e-d5d158925b19.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155169234-677ceed8-2cde-41de-bb86-62d3074d5353.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madeleine spent two weeks in Tromsø this month on the course “Fish-migrations; science, management and politics” at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.uit.no/startsida&quot;&gt;UiT&lt;/a&gt;, with a heavy focus on learning about various methods of telemetry and how to track fish movement (while she was there she was lucky enough to see some northern lights as well!). Now she’s focusing on planning the upcoming field season including setting up a smolt trap for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/about/maps/&quot;&gt;MAPS&lt;/a&gt; project in Haga Å.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155197053-96b5abb4-3b16-4b7b-9083-b9fb440db98d.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/155197207-31d6d484-c06f-4229-b219-537cfa996579.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More newsletters to come about SEG activities, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS in Denmark</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-denmark"/>
   <updated>2021-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-denmark</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;MAPS goes international!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denmark is the first stop on the MAPS European tour, seeing us working in the stream Gudsø in the region of Kolding. &lt;!--more--&gt; Over the course of a few days and with invaluable assistance from the Technical Univeristy of Denmark (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dtu.dk/&quot;&gt;DTU&lt;/a&gt;) we were able to tag approximately 200 fish in the Danish system, half just a few hundred metres from where the stream empties into Kolding fjord and half several kilometres upstream. And now we wait! After the spring migration season hopefully we see that some of our fish have moved out of the system and into the fjord to mature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;swiper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/148944986-1aff75a3-4715-4ba1-95f5-72b500282230.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/148945052-2c8342c2-015f-4d21-903b-a74b5647b205.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/148945123-2544f229-7b51-47f9-b099-5868cecc27b6.JPG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/148945172-5a69e899-767c-49f6-b5a5-68adbb25f59b.JPG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/148945273-f5afac1b-073f-489d-b74c-2d82d88a9edc.JPG&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-prev&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-next&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-pagination&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NOBROOK Autumn 2021</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-first-post"/>
   <updated>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/nobrook-first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The initial field work for the NOBROOK project has begun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This autumn we have started the process of tagging fish in several stream sections in Borås with both allopatric populations with only brown trout and sympatric populations of both brown trout and brook trout. &lt;!--more--&gt; In total we have tagged and collected data from around 400 fish. The following eight weeks after tagging we have been back to each stream section once per week and walked the stretches with portable antennas to track their movement. The final week we recaptured several of our tagged fish and measured their growth this fall. The rest of the winter we will plan for the next field season which will begin early spring!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;swiper&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-wrapper&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146347814-b6e99ae3-b28d-4ec0-9d6e-e47db0aed1b9.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146348127-2740c7bf-8b0c-4aa7-bc8f-b8c0e6f4d47e.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146348210-cde94411-fcd3-4495-b3e9-59161a829fc1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146348665-374db8c8-c63d-4e91-8b97-53aa3b61e920.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146348756-95e50468-5f98-4f35-a7a2-875f5277bee9.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-slide&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/146349386-1a68302c-28f0-4890-91ec-f3913a2a532b.jpg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-prev&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-button-next&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;swiper-pagination&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/33ojeSr5MmY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS Autumn 2021</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-first-post"/>
   <updated>2021-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//news/maps-first-post</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;MAPS begins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The autumn field season sees the MAPS project get underway in Sweden. Here we have chosen a Haga å, a small stream running through the town of Billdal, Gothenburg, as our main study system for the coming years. &lt;!--more--&gt; Our first task was to construct stationary PIT antennas throughout the system to monitor fish movement. After much trial and error, I am pleased to say there are now three functional antennas covering a wide stretch of the stream with more hopefully to be added in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the antennas in place, the next task was to find some fish to follow! Throughout the stream we managed to PIT tag almost 100 juvenile fish that could likely migrate out this following spring. A further 100 younger fish were also caught. After a brief stay at GU’s labs, where they underwent behavioural study by Matilda for her Master’s project, these smaller fish were also tagged and released back into Haga were hopefully we may see them migrate out spring 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>NOBROOK</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/projects/nobrook"/>
   <updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//projects/nobrook</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;evaluating-removal-methods-of-the-invasive-brook-trout-and-effects-of-removal-on-the-ecosystem&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evaluating removal methods of the invasive Brook trout and effects of removal on the ecosystem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall aim of the NOBROOK project is to develop new methods for removal of the invasive brook trout and to evaluate the effect of removal on ecosystems. Through establishing several control populations of known phenotypical distribution and a combination of brown trout in allopatry and in sympatry with brook trout be able to compare and test different removal methods across species and phenotypical traits. The response and recovery of the ecosystem after removal will we examined by investigating the composition of benthic invertebrates and fish diets as well as the potential impact presence of brook trout may have on the interaction between brown trout and the endangered freshwater pearl mussel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results will provide insights into the resilience of stream ecosystems and be helpful in efforts to restore and maintain the important ecosystem services and biodiversity connected to these habitats. This project is a part of The Swedish Environmental Protection Agency's &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturvardsverket.se/om-miljoarbetet/forskning/miljoforskning/forskningssatsningar-natur/hantering-av-invasiva-frammande-arter/&quot;&gt;management of invasive alien species program &lt;/a&gt;, and is divided into four work packages which you can read or hear more about below.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details class=&quot;publications-details&quot;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;publications-year&quot;&gt;Workpackage 1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the first WP the aim is to establish control populations and develop novel removal methods for brook trout.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; In WP1 we will initially assess the allopatric and sympatric populations. These populations inhabit eight different natural stream sections we have selected in the Borås area of western Sweden. We will sample approximately 50 fish form each section (in sympatric sections we will aim for 25 of each species): two streams have allopatric brown trout and sympatric brown and brook trout populations at different sections (Ringsbäcken and Lindåsabäcken). Hökabäcken has sympatric populations upstream and downstream, and Sävbäcken has allopatric upstream and downstream. We will catch fish using electro fishing and traps. We will tag each fish with Passive Integrated Transponders (PIT) tags, weigh and measure fork length and photograph each fish. We will be assessing the social hierarchy by utilizing a modified open field freeze test and count opercular beat rates, and habitat use by monitoring their movement over time using portable antenna. We will also assess their diets by using stable isotope analyses of carbon and nitrogen through sampling of pelvic fin clips (isotope content in fins correlate with that of muscle tissue and allows for non-lethal sampling) and potential prey, and growth by recapturing the tagged individuals later in the season. These will form our “control” populations where we have data on growth, diets and boldness. We will also examine some fundamental properties of each section including temperature, pH, productivity and rate of decomposition and nutrient cycling, in addition to examining the benthic invertebrate compositions of our stream sections using kick sampling. &lt;/p&gt;
  
&lt;p&gt;In the second part of this work package, we will test methods of removal. These methods include electrofishing, traps and nets. We will vary our electrofishing temporally and spatially in order to target more brook trout. Temporally this will be done at different times throughout the day as well as the season where we expect to find differences in capture rates and phenotypic traits depending on when we electro fish. We will also attempt to target brook trout where and when they spawn to reduce reproductive success. Different traps will be evaluated; “social” traps and traps baited with pheromones. In total, this work package will give use the comparable baseline information and the efficiency of several methods of removal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details class=&quot;publications-details&quot;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;publications-year&quot;&gt;Workpackage 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the second WP the aim is to study behavioral changes of both the invasive brook trout and the native sympatric brown trout (e.g. dispersal, trophic niche, habitat use) after removal/nearly removal of brook trout population. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; Brown trout tend to alter their niche and habitat use in sympatry with brook trout. In this WP we will assess to what extent these effects remain after removal. We will also investigate whether these effects are equally impacted by brook trout, or whether a few more dominant or bold individuals affect brown trout behavior to a larger extent. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details class=&quot;publications-details&quot;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;publications-year&quot;&gt;Workpackage 3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the third WP the focus will be on evaluating the ecosystem after removal &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;  Again, we will use the same stream sections as in WP1 allowing us to assess the composition of benthic invertebrates in the stream both in allopatric stretches and sympatric stretches as well as the composition of polyunsaturated fatty acids in brook and brown trout in sympatric and allopatric populations. The flux of emerging invertebrates will be quantified using emergence traps and their contribution to terrestrial consumers will be quantified using stable isotope analyses. We will also assess the stream section as they relate to functions including primary production, recycling of organic matter and nutrient cycling. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;details class=&quot;publications-details&quot;&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;publications-year&quot;&gt;Workpackage 4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the fourth and final WP we will focus on ecosystem effects as well; this time on the interaction between the endangered freshwater pearl mussel, brown trout and the invasive brook trout since all species often share habitats.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;  We will here focus on how brook trout and its phenotypic variability induced by removal may modulate interactions between a host (brown trout) and the parasite (larva of freshwater pearl mussel. Brook trout might have a direct negative effect on this relationship if brook trout gets infested but cannot produce juvenile mussels. However, there might also be indirect effects if the presence of brook trout would alter the temporal and/or spatial habitat use of brown trout resulting in fewer exposures to the glochidia larva. This WP will partly be performed in a different system than the other WP where we have a population of FPM. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To aim with WP4 is therefore to establish to which extent invasive brook trout can act as a functional host of FPM, and examine how this in turn affects the functionality of native brown trout as the main host for the glochidia larvae of the FPM, both direct and indirect. 
&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;video-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dfq0yNJo-J8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.naturvardsverket.se/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/149932141-fc1e04e5-d0bd-49b0-b392-814bc1c4b163.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://formas.se/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/149924302-a5e85e43-f5f8-4b2f-b1d3-dc389238b59d.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;News&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;

  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/brook-trout-a-management-conundrum&quot;&gt;
          Brook Trout; A Management Conundrum in Swedish Streams
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;03 Apr 2025&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;With their bright red markings with blue borders the brook trout (&lt;em&gt;Salvelinus fontinalis&lt;/em&gt;) is a charismatic fish popular with Swedish anglers.&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/brook-trout-a-management-conundrum&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/invasive-species-interactions-diet-and-personality&quot;&gt;
          Invasive species interactions, diet and personality
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;01 Apr 2025&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;How does it all fit together?&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/blog/invasive-species-interactions-diet-and-personality&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-in-austria&quot;&gt;
          Spring and summer in Austria for NOBROOK
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;02 Oct 2023&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This past May until August we finally ran the much anticipated experiments in the artificial stream channels in Lunz Am See, Austria!&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-in-austria&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-fall-and-winter&quot;&gt;
          Autumn and winter for the NOBROOK project
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;13 Feb 2023&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Progress is being made for the NOBROOK project!&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-fall-and-winter&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-second-post&quot;&gt;
          NOBROOK Spring 2022
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;25 Jun 2022&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The spring has been a busy time for the NOBROOK project!&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-second-post&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-first-post&quot;&gt;
          NOBROOK Autumn 2021
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;01 Sep 2021&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The initial field work for the NOBROOK project has begun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This autumn we have started the process of tagging fish in several stream sections in Borås with both allopatric populations with only brown trout and sympatric populations of both brown trout and brook trout.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/nobrook-first-post&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
&lt;/aside&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>MAPS</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/projects/maps"/>
   <updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//projects/maps</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;migratory-patterns-and-productivity-potential-of-juvenile-sea-trout&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Migratory patterns and productivity potential of juvenile sea trout&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAPS project is a PhD project looking to answer questions relating to the downstream migration of sea trout. There two main avenues of interest: building a model to predict smolt productivity and assessing differences between offspring of long and short distance migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sea trout are a valuable migratory species that provides both economic and ecosystem services. They are under threat from numerous angles including: climate change, aquaculture and habitat destruction. Thus research that can help protect them by guiding management/restoration projects is vital. During migration from a freshwater environment to marine environment is a period of extreme vulnerability and understanding what happens during this time is key to boosting population numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will examine smolt production potential with the aim to produce a standardised method for assessing productivity and reveal associations with habitat quality. Smolt traps will be run in streams across the sea trouts natural range to give estimates of juvenile densities. Each stream will be habitat mapped in detail including and combined with juvenile density data to create a predictive model. 
Mechanisms behind differing migration strategies will be questioned in behavioural and physiological studies, in particular offspring of long and short distance migrants will be compared. When sea trout return from the marine environment they can migrate upstream a few hundred metres or many kilometres, this research will reveal whether the there are differences in the offspring related to variation in migration distance of the parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/150122386-568745c4-b91e-4d09-856c-dca3ab7856c8.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telemetry will provide a wealth of movement data from streams across Europe with a particular focus on migration timings and residency vs. anadromy. Using in stream PIT antenna systems we will be able to closely monitor movement within streams and analyse differences between individuals, for example whether there is a sex bias in migrants, or if age at first migration differs between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://formas.se/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/149924302-a5e85e43-f5f8-4b2f-b1d3-dc389238b59d.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ices.dk/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/96004332/149924529-7370b8e2-2ef1-4db1-91a0-7f7f60acadc6.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;News&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;

  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-portugal&quot;&gt;
          MAPS in Portugal
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;19 Sep 2023&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;MAPS heads south!&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-portugal&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/new-year-for-maps&quot;&gt;
          New year for MAPS
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;05 Feb 2023&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;A new year for MAPS with lots of exciting work in the pipeline! Plans for a habitat mapping workshop, setting up new stationary antennas and fieldwork in sunny Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/new-year-for-maps&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-norway&quot;&gt;
          MAPS in Norway
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;21 Sep 2022&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;SEG heads North.&lt;/p&gt;



    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-norway&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-summer-2022&quot;&gt;
          MAPS Summer 2022
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;01 Aug 2022&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At the end of May Johan and Madeleine set off to France for a few days to check out a potential stream site for the MAPS project.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-summer-2022&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-antennas&quot;&gt;
          Stationary antennas for MAPS
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;21 Mar 2022&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The antennas are working!&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-antennas&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-denmark&quot;&gt;
          MAPS in Denmark
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;24 Sep 2021&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;MAPS goes international!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denmark is the first stop on the MAPS European tour, seeing us working in the stream Gudsø in the region of Kolding.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-denmark&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-first-post&quot;&gt;
          MAPS Autumn 2021
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;01 Sep 2021&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;MAPS begins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The autumn field season sees the MAPS project get underway in Sweden. Here we have chosen a Haga å, a small stream running through the town of Billdal, Gothenburg, as our main study system for the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/maps-first-post&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
&lt;/aside&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Eelgrass and sea trout project</title>
   <link href="https://seggothenburg.com/projects/eelgrass"/>
   <updated>1970-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>https://seggothenburg.com//projects/eelgrass</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eelgrass and sea trout project is a project funded by Interreg Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the ZOsteRa RestOration group (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gu.se/en/research/zorro&quot;&gt;ZORRO&lt;/a&gt;) at University of Gothenburg, this project aims to understand the importance of shallow coastal areas for sea trout smolt. By combining various telemetry techniques with capturing methods such as beach seine nets and fyke nets, we hope to determine how shallow coastal areas i.e. eelgrass meadows and unvegetated sites affect prey choice, growth, survival and habitat use of sea trout. The results can provide information about the need to co-manage sea trout and eelgrass meadows in the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;sponsors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interregeurope.eu/&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img alt=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/73ea06cb-2906-4d66-9947-c12c4d0eac50&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;aside class=&quot;posts&quot;&gt;
  &lt;header&gt;
    &lt;h4&gt;News&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;/header&gt;

  
  &lt;section class=&quot;post&quot;&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
      &lt;h4 class=&quot;post-title&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/eelgrass-project-first-post&quot;&gt;
          Eelgrass and sea trout project 2024 field season
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;post-date&quot;&gt;01 Feb 2025&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;During the field season of 2024 we PIT-tagged migrating smolts in four streams along the Swedish west coast and followed up by conducting a beach seine net survey in the coastal area adjacent to the streams.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;footer style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;&gt;
      &lt;a href=&quot;https://seggothenburg.com/news/eelgrass-project-first-post&quot; style=&quot;color:#000;&quot;&gt; Read More &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/footer&gt;
  &lt;/section&gt;
  
&lt;/aside&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
